Guide to the Administrative Papers of the Chancellor Henry Mitchell MacCracken 1884-1910 RG.3.0.3
New York University Archives
- Series III: Physical Plant
  Real estate material describes the purchase of property from the Mali and Schwab estates, as well as the Ohio Society's assistance in obtaining property originally belonging to Loring Andrews. Limited correspondence about the sale or rental of property is included.
  Building construction, furnishing, and maintenance files include internal memoranda and reports from the building committee, which consisted of members of the University Council, and correspondence with McKim, Meade and White, the principal architects at University Heights. MacCracken's correspondence with Stanford White documents the design of Gould Memorial Library and the Hall of Fame Colonnade. Also included in the records is correspondence and plans with various contractors and builders of the buildings at University Heights.
  Municipal improvements and services records consist of correspondence suggesting the desire of the area's residents to improve city services and to establish such cultural institutions as the Presbyterian church and a branch library. The notebook of the church, minutes of meetings, and some financial information. Printed material includes flyers for the sale of lots, as well as programs for the opening day celebrations in 1895.
  - Washington Square
    - Plans for construction, 1892-1893 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Plans for preserving original University building, ca. 1892 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Sewerage agreement, 1892 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - McKim, Mead & White, 1892 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Rentals, 1893, 1900 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Alfred Zucker; American Book Co., 1894 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Alfred Zucker; American Book Co., 1895 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Alfred Zucker; American Book Co., 1896 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Alfred Zucker; Leslie J. Tompkins, 1899-1900 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Main Building: Zucker Plans, ca. 1894 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Main Building, Rental of, 1901-1904 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Bills, 1889-1891 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - University Heights
    - Purchase and sale of property, 1892-1908 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Summary of purchase and subscription list, 1891-1892 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, subscription book, 1892-1905 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Members, 1892, Undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Printed material, 1891, 1893 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Property taxes, 1893-1902 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Schwab estate funding, newspaper clippings re, 1906 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Legal agreements, 1894-1900 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Deeds and mortgages, ca. 1893-1910 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - University Heights North, 1893-1894 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - University Heights East, 1893 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - University Heights West, 1892-1893 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - University Heights South, 1907 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Flyer: University Heights - The New Site of the Undergraduate College...; reverse side, Map of New York City Showing the Interests of the University of the City of New York, ca. 1892-1894 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Flyer: University Heights - The New Site of the Undergraduate College, of the Graduate Seminary (in part), and of the Engineering School of New York University according to the plans of Vaux & Co., Landscape Architects, ca. 1896 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - "Some New Plans and Construction", 1896-1897 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Maps, diagrams, and blueprints, ca. 1892-1908 (Box 18, Folder 8, Flat-file-folder 3)
    - Internal correspondence, resolutions, financial statements, 1893-1902, Undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1896-1897 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1898-1902 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Photograph of drawing of proposed Heights Campus incorporating original University building, 1894 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Architectural drawings, ca. 1893-1900 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Specifications - Library, 1896 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Specifications - Museum, 1896 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Bills, 1896-1902 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - M. Reid & Company (mason and builder), 1896-1897 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Pattison Brothers (electrical engineers), 1898-1901 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Hatzel and Buehler (electrical engineers), 1898-1899 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - George Mason (civil engineer), Undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Augustus Noll (electrical engineer), 1896-1900 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Conduit Wiring Company (electric light plant wiring), 1898 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Archer and Pancoast Company (light fixtures), 1896-1898 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Mitchell Vance Company (light fixtures), 1900-1901, Undated (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Alfred R. Wolff (consulting engineer), 1894-1899 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Charles B. Brush and Company (civil engineer), 1894, 1896, 1906 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Baldwin Engineering Company (steam mains, boiler), 1897-1901 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Baker, Smith and Company (steam mains), 1897 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - George I. Roberts and Brothers (steam pipes), 1897-1900 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Collins P. Bliss (architect and engineer, director of testing lab), 1897, 1899-1904 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1897-1900 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Bills, payroll, 1898-1900, 1905 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Library Bureau (furniture), 1896-1898 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Howard Clarke/Clarke and Baker (furniture), 1899-1900 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - L. A. Schwarzwaelder (furniture), 1899-1901 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - R. W. Reid & Company (furniture), 1899 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Self-winding Clock Company, 1894-1899 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Tiffany Glass Company (woodwork and glass), 1898-1902 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Various organ companies, 1899-1900 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous companies, 1893-1904, 1909 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Andrew H. Green Laboratory, 1904
    - Gould Residence Hall, ca. 1896 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Sedgwick Avenue Park, 1897-1901, Undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Streets: Proposed new street, 1902, 1906 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Streets: 180th St. improvement, 1906-1909 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Sewer system, 1896, 1908 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Rapid Transit System, 1900-1906 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - N.Y.C. Interborough Railway Company, 1902-1903, 1906 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - New York Central and Hudson Railroad Company, 1894-1895, 1903-1907 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Telephone, Telegraph, and Post Office, 1892-1895, 1900-1908 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Police and Fire Protection, 1899, 1902, 1904 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Civic organizations, 1893, 1901-1906 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - New York Public Library, 1901 (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence re acquisition of site and selection of denomination, 1894-1904 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Secretary's notebook, 1895-1900 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and papers, 1896-1900 (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Student Affairs and Activities
  The student affairs folders contain correspondence from and about students describing admissions, courses, transfers, grades, reasons for leaving N.Y.U., and publication of the class annual, the Violet. Information about student regulations, chapel attendance, petitions, and fraternities also is included. Other records document the development of an athletic program. Letters giving reasons for leaving the University are arranged alphabetically by correspondent. All other material is arranged in chronological order within folders.
  - Admissions, 1894-1910 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Courses, transfers, grades, 1893-1895, 1900-1910 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Reasons for leaving, A-Z, 1902 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Violet (yearbook), 1894-1910 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Student Regulations, 1892, 1901-1902 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Chapel Attendance, 1900-1909, Undated (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Petitions, 1895-1909 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Fraternities, 1892-1893, 1900-1910 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Job applicants, 1894-1895 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - N.Y.U. Athletic Association, 1901-1907, Undated (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and paper; honors program; faculty recommendations for improving scholarship, 1900-1910, Undated (Box 25, Folder 8)
- Series V: Governance
  These records consist of limited correspondence and minutes of the New York University Council and the University Senate, which was established in 1896. A limited amount of material concerns a proposed merger between N.Y.U. and Columbia University in 1892. Much of the council material describes the Alumni Association's efforts to gain representation on the University's governing board.
  - University Council
    - Minutes, reports, correspondence, 1893-1909, Undated (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Alumni Association representation, 1891, 1907-1910 (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Proposed N.Y.U.-Columbia merger, 1892, 1894 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Charles Butler gift; correspondence re Union Theological Seminary, 1890-1896 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - University Senate
    - Minutes and Correspondence, 1896-1897, 1901 1903 Undated (Box 26, Folder 3)
- Series VI: External Relations
  Material in this series includes legislation proposed by or affecting the University, and correspondence with several Boards of Education, the Association of American Universities, the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, and other universities and organizations.
  - Legislation, 1893-1900 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Legislation, 1902-1907, Undated (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - State and City Boards of Education, 1892-1912, Undated (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Association of American Universities, 1901-1903 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, 1907-1909 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Other universities and organizations, 1894-1895, 1900-1905 (Box 26, Folder 9)
- Series VII: Public Relations
  These files contain typescripts of press releases from 1901 to 1910, correspondence and typescripts of History of New York University, by Ernest G. Sihler and Henry M. MacCracken (1901), business correspondence about the University's publications and material describing various celebrations in which New York University participated.
  - Press Releases, 1901 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Press Releases, 1902 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Press Release, 1903 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Press Releases, 1904 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Press Releases, 1905 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Press Releases, 1906 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Press Releases, 1907 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Press Releases, 1908 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Press Releases, 1909 (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Press Releases, 1910 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Advertisements, 1896-1897 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - Universities and Their Sons: New York University (Boston: R. Herndon & Co., 1901)
    - Correspondence, 1898-1903 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Sketch of history of University presumably written by Henry M. MacCracken (various drafts), ca. 1898-1899 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Jay Gould: Biographical sketch, written by H. MacCracken, ca. 1898-1899 (Box 27, Folder 14)
  - Publications
    - The Macmillan Company, 1899-1901 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Other publishers, 1893-1908, Undated (Box 27, Folder 16)
  - Participation in Celebrations
    - New York Columbian Celebration, 1892-1893 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Paris Exposition, 1900 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Pan-American Exposition, 1901 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1903-1904 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Plans for exhibit space; other printed material, 1903-1904(?) (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Photographs of exhibit, 1904 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Explanation of exhibit as rationale of organization of New York University, ca. 1900 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Diamond Anniversary (University's semisesquicentennial--75th, 1901-1905 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Edgar Allen Poe Centennial, 1909 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Hudson-Fulton anniversaries, 1909 (Box 28, Folder 10)
- Series VIII: Alumni Affairs and Activities
  The folders on alumni activities include material on the General Alumni Society, and correspondence from several specialized alumni groups. Lists of all graduates from 1833 to 1892 and the subsequent classes of 1896, 1897, and 1900 are supplemented by the names of those graduates who had served in the Civil War, and Phi Beta Kappa members prior to 1896.
  - Correspondence, 1902, 1905-1909 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Printed Material, 1891-1910 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Alumni Association, 1896 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1900-1902, 1910 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Alumnae Electorate, 1909 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Law School Alumni, 1900-1910 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Lists of graduates (including classes of 1833-1892, 1896, 1897, 1900) (Box 29, Folder 7)
- Series IX: Honorary Degrees
  Information on honorary degrees consists of biographical sketches and correspondence with applicants and recipients, including several women and some notable men. Material within the honorary degrees correspondence folders is arranged alphabetically by individual. All other material is arranged in chronological order within folders.
  - Biographical sketches, 1904-1910 (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Applicants, 1898 (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - Recipients -- William R. Day, 1899 (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Applicants, 1899 (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - Recipients -- Philip R. Uhler and William Fiske Wood, 1900 (Box 29, Folder 12)
  - Applicants, 1900 (Box 29, Folder 13)
  - Recipients -- Emily Ogden Butler, Anna Palmer Draper, Martha Buell Munn, Catherine Bacon Smith, 1902 (Box 29, Folder 14)
  - Recipients -- Vincent Pisek, John Rutherford Wright, Charles A. Gardiner, 1903 (Box 29, Folder 15)
  - Applicants, 1903 (Box 29, Folder 16)
  - Recipients, Master of Letters -- Ida M. Bodman, Frank Wilson Lindsley, Margaret Olivia Slocum Sage, 1904 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Recipients, Doctor of Divinity -- Jesse Brush, Morris W. Leibert, Harry P. Nichols, Wilson D. Sexton, 1904 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Recipients, Doctor of Laws -- Willard Bartlett, Elihu Root, Fritz Zinsser, 1904 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Applicants, 1904 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Recipients, Doctor of Divinity -- Henry Sloan Coffin, Lewis Bayles Paton, Robert Livingston Rudolph, 1906 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Recipients, Doctor of Laws -- Alexander Crombie Humphreys, Martin J. Keogh, 1906 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Applicants, 1906 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Recipients, Doctor of Divinity -- Henry M. Brown, Stanley White, 1907 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Recipients, Doctor of Laws -- Joseph D. Bryant, Charles Warren Hunt, George Filmore Swain, John Woodward, 1907 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Applicants, 1907 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Recipients, Master of Letters -- Helen Gray Cone, Edward Hagaman Hall, 1908 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - Recipients, Doctor of Laws -- George Samler Davis, 1908 (Box 30, Folder 12)
  - Applicants, 1908 (Box 30, Folder 13)
  - Recipients, Doctor of Divinity -- Frank De Witt Talmage, 1909 (Box 30, Folder 14)
  - Applicants, 1909 (Box 30, Folder 15)
  - Recipients, Doctor of Commercial Science -- Lawrence O. Murray, 1910 (Box 30, Folder 16)
  - Recipients, Doctor of Divinity -- George Law Richmond, George Godhart Vogel, 1910 (Box 30, Folder 17)
  - Recipients, Doctor of Laws -- James Brooks Dill, Egbert Le Fevre; negative responses, 1910 (Box 30, Folder 18)
  - Applicants, 1910 (Box 30, Folder 19)
- Series X: Expansion and Fundraising
  The expansion and fundraising series contains correspondence, maps, clippings, and legal documents relating to the development and growth of NYU from the late 1880s through 1924. The series also includes speeches and articles written by MacCracken and others in support of the University's goals. Topics include potential sites for additional campus buildings, mergers with other New York City universities, and donor relations. Other materials found in this section relate to commencement activities.
  - A Few Facts as to New York University on Its Business Side, undated (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - A Few Facts with Conclusions Drawn Therefrom, undated (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Address to the Citizens of New York, undated (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Aquisition of Graduate House and Property, 1921-1924 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Carnegie, Andrew Correspondence, 1906 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Chancellor's Statement-University Heights South, 1907 October 31 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Commencement Week 1907 Clippings (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Copies of the New Yorker (The NYU Weekly), 1913 February-March, October (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - DeForest, Robert W Correspondence regarding Mrs. Russell Sage and Schwab Estate, 1906-1907 (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Donations Account Book, undated (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - Excerpt from the Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1892 November 4 (Box 31, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence Relating to Fundraising and Exspansion of NYU, 1906-1911, undated (Box 31, Folder 12)
  - Hughes, Charles Evan, 1907, 1916 (Box 31, Folder 13)
  - Law School Merger Clippings, 1895 April (Box 31, Folder 14)
  - Maps of Potential NYU Expansion Locations, undated (Box 31, Folder 15, Flat-file-folder 1 Left)
  - Minuted of a Special Meeting of the Executive Committee, 1903 June 5 (Box 31, Folder 16)
  - NYU: Move Uptown, 1890s (Box 31, Folder 17)
  - New York Assembly Act for Creation of Park, 1906 (Box 31, Folder 18)
  - NYU and Colombia and Other Mergers Documents, 1909 (Box 31, Folder 19)
  - NYU Commencement Calendar and Clippings, 1903 (Box 31, Folder 20)
  - NYU Founders Day at University Heights Press Clippings, 1895 April (Box 31, Folder 21)
  - Obituaries for Howard Crosby, Chancellor of NYU 1870-1880, 1891 (Box 31, Folder 22)
  - Petition on Behalf of New York University, undated (Box 31, Folder 23)
  - Record of John Johnston, Esq. and John Taylor Johnston, LL.D. in regard to their connection with New York University, 1830-1893, 1906 (Box 31, Folder 24)
  - Sage, Mrs. Russell Correspondence, 1907 (Box 31, Folder 25)
  - The School of Pedagogy-Its Aims and the Opportunities It Affords, 1898 (Box 31, Folder 26)
  - The University: Past, Present, and Future by Philip Schaff, 1889 (Box 31, Folder 27)
  - The X__ Y__ Foundation for American Education, undated (Box 31, Folder 28)
- Duplicate Manuscript Materials (Box 34, Box 35, Box 36, Box 3a, Box 4a)